PIXAR IN A BOX 艾墨镇 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox
PIXAR IN A BOX 艾墨镇 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox
- In the previous video, we saw how to compute
- 在上一个视频中 我们明白了如何计算
an intersection point, I, that lies in the plane
一个位于三角形所在平面内的
of a triangle.
交点
But how can we tell if the point is like this one,
但我们如何确定一个点是像这样
that's inside the triangle; or like this one,
落在三角形之内 或是像这样
that's outside the triangle?
落在三角形之外呢？
The method our ray tracer actually uses makes use
光线追踪渲染器实际上使用的是
of vector algebra.
向量运算
But a method that is essentially the same is easy
但有一种方法本质上和它一样
to explain if you understand weighted averages.
而且更容易解释 那就是加权平均数
(bell)
（叮铃铃）
Notice that as I change the weights in the average,
注意到当我改变权重的时候
the intersection point, I, moves.
交点 I 也跟着改变了
And if all the weights are positive,
如果所有的权重都是正值
I is inside the triangle.
I 就在三角形内部
But look what happens when one
但如果有一个或
or more weights is negative:
多个权重为负值时：
I escapes from the triangle.
I 就离开了三角形
Bingo!
就是这样！
If we can determine the weights needed to produce I,
如果我们能确定产生 I 的权重
we can simply check their signs.
我们就仅用检查它们的正负即可
If one or two of them is negative,
如果它们中有一个或两个是负的
I is outside the triangle,
I 就在三角形外部
and otherwise, I is inside.
其他情况下 I 就在内部
But how can we determine the weights?
但我们如何确定权重？
Let's leave them as unknowns for the moment,
让我们先把它们当成未知数
and we'll call them little a, little b, and little c.
我们称它们为小 a、小 b 和小 c
Every point I in the plane of big A, big B, and big C
每个落在点大 A、大 B 和大 C 所确定的平面上的点 I
can be written as a weighted average
都可以用大 A、大 B 和大 C的
of big A, big B, and big C.
加权平均数表示
If I pick little a, little b, and little c,
如果我选择特定的小 a、小 b 和小 c
so that they add to one,
使它们加起来等于 1
then I can forget about the denominator.
我就可以忽略分母了
The resulting equation,
得到的方程就是
I equals little a times big A
I = a*A+b*B+c*C
represents the following three equations:
代表了三个方程
one for the x-coordinate,
一个是 X 轴向的
one for the y-coordinate,
一个是 Y 轴向的
and one for the z.
一个是 Z 轴向的
We know I, big A, big B, and big C,
我们知道 I、大 A、大 B 和大 C
so the only unknowns are little a, little b, and little c.
所以未知数仅为小 a、小 b 和小 c
So this is three equations and three unknowns
所以这是三个方程和三个未知数
that can be solved for the values of little a,
我们可以解出小 a
little b, and little c.
小 b 和小 c 的值
Once you know little a, little b, and little c,
一旦你知道了小 a、小 b 和小 c 的值
check their signs to determine if I is inside the triangle.
检查它们的符号就知道 I 是否在三角形内部
In this final exercise, you'll be asked
在最后的练习中 你将会被要求
to compute intersection points I,
计算焦点 I
and determine if they lie inside or outside the triangle.
并确定它们落在三角形的内部还是外部
Now, after all that, go forth and write your own ray tracer. aimozhen.com/pixarinabox
现在 了解了这么多之后 接着向前推进并写出你自己的光线追踪渲染器吧 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox